welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
hi I'm baby gray I'm here to welcome you
all to the stoah the stoah is a place
for us to cook here and dialogue about
what matters most on the knife's edge of
what's happening now and this is the
debut session of a new series that I'll
be hosting I may be gray and the series
is about raw sexuality so our first
guest is cabeza heady he's the director
of I am a sex addict the show about the
show and other radical honest very meta
self-reflexive TV shows and films uh I
was really inspired in particular by an
interview that cavae did recently in
last December with brick TVs glitter and
doom about Radek radical honesty I feel
like it touched on a lot of the topics
that we've been talking about here at
the stoah and so I'm really excited to
talk to him about some of the issues
that he talked about there I think that
it's probably okay to start getting into
the questions there might still be a few
people trickling in as we get started
but carve a there there is something
that you said in the glitter and doom
interview that I really liked you said
that every interaction is a microcosm
for the whole of humanity's interactions
and that resonated with me a lot and it
gets to the heart of why I wanted to do
a series on raw sexuality at this
particular moment at the stoah I think
that we share this idea that there is
something to do with being radically
honest about our sex lives that relates
to the big issues in the world today and
I was wondering if you could talk a
little bit about why honesty on a
personal level is important on a
political level I mean I think I just I
guess I feel like we don't know anything
I mean I study philosophy and like after
st. vaast I was like okay no one knows
anything it was kind of like
my take-home and it's like if you don't
know anything you really don't know what
would be the right thing to do at any
moment it's like you really don't know
but if it's just honest about whatever
you're feeling we're thinking then it
was just kind of like oh just sort of
take care of itself like you don't have
to you have to manipulate reality to get
to the place where you think you should
go you can just like not do that
and so to me like it's about giving up
an agenda or a destination and just sort
of like letting the truth of them of the
situation just sort of unfold
organically and that seems to me like it
avoids a lot of wrong minded thinking
about what should be or and
misinformation about what it is because
we don't know I mean we just don't know
but we do know how we feel and we do
know what's true for us and that's all
we really do know yeah and in your films
it seems that this honesty is the sort
of compass for you that that directs all
of your films usually your shows and
your films don't have a script the show
about the show each episode is about the
making of the episode before and I think
that it's it reminds me a lot of improv
we we talk sometimes about impro by
keith johnston here at the ZOA
and a lot of us are into the like
uncertainty and being and unknowingness
and I wonder if you could talk a little
bit about how all of the uncertainty
around the Kovach crisis has affected
your love life and your sex life and if
that's had any repercussions through
your art since it's always so self
reflexive I mean it's been good for me
might be good for my sex life actually
and I'm having a relationship right now
with somebody online who lives in Berlin
and we met online just she was she she
was a fan of of my work and we started
talking and it's been like incredibly
intense and kind of amazing I mean I
don't know if this would have happened
if we were
having this quarantine and my heart has
just been really wide open because of it
so for me it's been really good
I'm really curious can you say any more
about why you think it might have been
like partially because of the unique
quarantine situation that you've been so
open hearted in this new relationship I
mean I think it's forced everyone to
slow down its first everyone kind of to
take stock of what's important and it
just seems like a wake-up call to
everybody at all levels and it also has
provided like the kind of alone time
that we don't get enough of usually and
I think you know like we can talk for
hours on the phone or whatever because
we're in this kind of period when people
aren't really working you know like work
has been sowed if you shut down so so
yeah it just is like a forced a
meditation retreat really and I think in
that space things things arise that
wouldn't arise if you were you know on
the treadmill of getting ahead
yeah that's really interesting I'm gonna
be talking to cadre until about the half
hour and then I'll switch to a questions
from you guys so if you guys have
questions that come up for you while
we're discussing please feel free to put
them in the chat and I'll be looking at
them in the next little while but I want
to get back to what you said about that
the pandemic has been sort of like a
meditation retreat I know that one of
the things that I've seen sort of in the
in the media around the pandemic is that
we're all going through this mass trauma
together and there's been sort of a
heavy way that it's been phrased to us
and and to think of it as that we're all
I mean and emitted li involuntarily
together on this sort of meditation
retreat feels like a more uplifting way
to look at it do you feel the same way
yeah I think might as well look at it in
the Alif lifting way what what what do
you think there is to be gained from
being on a meditation retreat with the
whole world it was well one thing I've
noticed is like I mean this has been
happening for years just the sort of the
way everyone is sort of more and more
connected you know and I think like I
use I used to edit with people you know
every day and they'd come to my
apartment and it was nice I enjoyed it
they would come over edit but now I'm
editing with people like all over the
you know all over the place and there's
no more boundaries so you're not
geographic boundaries in the same way
and you know I think there's this sense
in which we're all one and in which you
know consciousness is collective and
there's something about the technology
of it and the forced zoom this of it
that kind of brings it together I mean
it's really weird I mean there's all
these people here in this space and it's
almost like we're we're one mind or
something like a hive mind or something
and I think
that's been increased since the
coronavirus hearing that I noticed the
word boundaries felt like emphatic for
you I know from watching your work that
sometimes you've had almost like a
position of being against boundaries and
wanting everybody to be able to be
connected and honest with each other and
working together is is there a way that
you've like gone out of your way to take
advantage of the boundaries that have
dissolved in this situation out of my
way
no I just think I mean boundaries are
weird I mean I'm not very good with
boundaries like I'm like I don't like
them and I don't think I have good
boundaries and I and I know that there's
something good about boundaries but I
mostly experience the Meza as a problem
or as a limitation that I that I chafe
against I took African drumming classes
for a while and I remember the teacher
would say like if you when you're
drumming you know everyone has a
different beat that they're doing and if
you are too intent on the other person's
beat like you're listening too carefully
to them you lose your own beat and then
you screw up the rhythm and but if you
also like our to focus on doing your own
be right you don't hear what they're
doing and you also script the rhythm and
there was a delicate balance between
keeping your beat and being and hearing
the other person's beat that was really
tricky and it's kind of almost like you
just hard not to lose it you know
constantly and then you kind of find it
again you know there's a quote by Kafka
I like a lot he says uh the true way is
like a rope that is stretched not at any
great height but just above the ground
it seems almost as it was put there to
make you stumble over it rather than to
be walked on and and the true way it
feels like this very tricky thing that's
so much like the actual way and it's
just this very minor difference that
you're constantly getting tripped up on
but
yeah I'm just I'm just riffing on
boundaries but there's something about
like and even here you know like there's
a like there's all these people in the
in the room and I'm like oh there's all
these people are they okay I hope
they're okay is this going on too long
should we should we open it up sooner
you know like there's a and then also if
I do it too much I'm not even like in my
own thing you know and being expressive
I'm just being worried or something but
you you want both energies and finding
that balance I think is is the tricky
thing in life in general and I think the
Xoom think is more to moved it into this
place where it's more focused you know
and it's almost like a pinpoint of
attention and you know there's certain
senses that are gone like touch and
smell and taste are not in that but the
rest of it it's like when you're blind
you you hear better like you know
there's something that is that is
intensified right when I was in clown
school there was an exercise we did
where one of the partners would put out
a finger and then you would connect the
fingers and one of the partners would
agree to close their eyes and be led
around in a room full of other clowns
just by the fingertip of the clown that
had their eyes open and there was such a
magical intimacy in um trusting each
other that way whether you were leading
somebody or you were the follower there
was such a surrender and such a giving
up of other sensory input you you had to
focus so much on that one little point
of connection and I think that that
relates to the way that the zune called
creates constraints that can actually
hack into the maseeh rather than hinder
it I think that that's a really exciting
way to look at it I know that a lot of
your work looks at trying to break other
kinds of boundaries and limitations
especially ones around sexual shame I
I know I am a sex addict was especially
aimed at trying to like have a voice in
a narrative around sex addiction that's
often like very shame on you
I'd love to hear you talk a little bit
about that I mean shame is like my
middle name I mean I just feel it all
the time and and I think you know like
this person that I've started seeing I
guess you know through zoom you know
like we kind of are like you know we're
sexual in this the energy is sexual and
we're both like wanting to have sex and
yeah we can't and so what do you do and
and it's I don't know like last night I
was sort of trying to explore this and
I'm not I'm not I'm not very good at
whatever online sex I don't I don't
really understand it or or you know it
doesn't it's never drawn me you know
ever it was drawn to it but it was like
what would it mean to have sex with
somebody when you can't be with them you
know what does that look like I you know
and I think a lot of it had to do with
with verbalizing I make for me it was
like verbalizing ones desire felt like
sex or verbalizing one sexual desire or
verbalizing this the particularity that
one's sexual desire because so much to
say about sex for me is about shame
being healed and about like doing the
thing that you're a little bit of shade
of but doing it anyway and the person
not judging you for it like that's what
sexual ecstasy sort of seems like to me
it's like a breaking of taboos and
boundaries and affirmations cellphone
vation and affirmation from the other
and mutually so it seems like if that's
what sexy is on some level you can do
that on zoom' it just means that you
have to you know trust the other person
and overcome your shame and take risks
take risks of being rejected and stuff
sexually or of your the specifics of
your sexual desire not necessarily
meeting the other person specifics and
you know
we just started to explore you that last
night I'm not advanced or anything in it
but it did feel like that was a way cuz
like you know we're thinking maybe we
could see each other like in two months
you know based on when the borders open
up and you know how do we get through
those two months it was like we need
some we need something because it's just
a maddening to just to wait and and you
wanna you don't want to wait in life you
want to just be in your bliss now
whatever that bliss is and find bliss in
the present and in the presence
limitations
you
and they're right we're always like
trying to find the bliss that's
available within the constraints of
whatever now we are you know inherently
traps in I hear a lot from you in your
work too about like a drive for novelty
and I hear in your life a lot of
ambivalence over the years around this
what I what I see is a natural desire
for newness how how would you relate
your like desire for novelty to the
highest spiritual conception you have of
yourself what's your defense of novelty
as like a spiritual passion well I think
God is always new I mean I think God is
the eternal newness of the moment being
recreated in each moment I mean it's
like new new new new new new you know
and I think what we do as humans is we
kind of like well one we're scared of
the new so we kind of like try to think
of experience than you based on some
previous concept that had to do with the
previous new but is not the current new
and so you know I think I think we're
all kind of control freaks and we're all
think that if we could just I don't know
whatever it is even if it's like I want
to take the trash out you know and then
like that's my goal I'm gonna take the
trash out now like even that is too much
like you know like because then you're
like not even like you're not paying
attention to the the the trek down the
stairs to the trashcan you're just like
in the trash getting done and there's
like a an incredible bliss to be had of
just like I'm gonna walk towards the
trash can and I don't know where what's
going to happen and so
maybe I'm not even gonna get to the
trashcan maybe like something will
happen along the way and I won't take
out the trash oh I'll get sidetracked
and that's and that's good or that's
fine so I just know that my own fears
have a lot to do with fearing I'm having
no faith I mean I think I'm not the only
person but I think it's hot most people
don't have faith that there is a
Providence or there's a reason whether
there's a meaning for what's happening
and so we're always fighting it and
being like oh shit that wasn't well you
know should have happened but I think
I'm trying to like surrender to a higher
knowledge than my own you know limited
ego knowledge of what I think would
would help me feel better and and I you
know and you know the saying a a you
know because I'd spent a lot of years in
a a meetings you know your best thinking
has gotten you here you know best thing
has gotten you in a room where you're
like I have a problem so you know my
thinking is not you know my thinking has
not helped doesn't help and there is a
kind of knowing I think that is beyond
thinking that is a spiritual knowing
which i think is what we need to tap
into but also just like a surrender at
every moment of like this isn't a little
example my idea of what it should
resemble and what is there what is the
newness of that that is actually here
presenting yourself to me for for
reception like to receive it and most
the time I'm not receiving the world I'm
just not like I'm like no thank you i I
have I have other plans you know and and
that is actually the opposite of bliss
and it's the opposite of art and it's
the opposite of spirituality to I think
it's just like Oh or is that
spirituality or something so just
I don't know if just being really
receptive to how the moment is different
than the moment a moment ago and and
then how that keeps happening there's a
weird delay here I answer your question
then there's like a long pause just like
really enjoying it to even break the
silence because I'm just savoring the
way that you've described impermanence I
really love the Buddhist and like hindu
concepts of things being continuous and
momentary in their own ways and it's
it's just really I don't know delicious
to hear your take on it
I I was planning to ask you kind of for
your other side of your ambivalence or a
novelty to what what part of it like
drives you crazy and like makes you mad
at yourself
what part of novelty am i against what
part of your own like drive towards
novelty feels like something that draws
you away from your own highest
spirituality um I don't I'm not aware of
any ambivalence about about novelty I
think about for novelty are you are you
afraid to something specific yeah mostly
just the I am a sex addict and having
like a desire to pursue sex with other
women outside of the relationship that
you're trying to manage or something
like that oh right right like monogamy
you mean something like that yeah yeah I
mean I think there is novelty to be had
in any situation for sure I mean there
is I mean I think the difficulty of
relationships is they they feel stale
after a while and I think that staleness
has a lot to do with our own mental
staleness that we project onto the other
I'm the other thing I noticed when I get
stoned which I love to do is the person
that I'm talking to you like you for
example maybe you know like I don't have
a concept of you and when I talk to you
I'm imposing my concept of you on you
and it's even just the way you look like
I like you have a face like I kind of
like saw your face once and it kind of
got
in my mind and then when you talk your
face is changing every second and you
have like a thousand different faces but
I'm just seeing that one face that I
that I remembered and that I'm
projecting onto your face but when I'm
stoned I'm like oh whoa she looks
totally different then she was looking
when I wasn't stoned and you're looking
different every every second or several
times a second and it's just like oh
there's sadness oh there's there's humor
and odours anger and oh there's joy I
know there's sexiness and oh there's you
know jealousy and oh there's you know
and it's just like I can't I can't
encompass you you're just like always
morphing on me and and and I love that
I'm just like and I'm just receptive and
I'm just like whoa who the hell are you
and I don't I don't know and I don't
need to know but you're not what I
thought you were and there's a sense of
the other power and sacredness that
arises from that and I think one of the
problems with monogamy is you lose that
sense of their the others power and
sacredness you know they become you know
their kin flat and it's like oh I know
what for example I know what it's like
to have sex with with you for example
but I don't I mean I might have had that
before but I haven't had like the one
I'm gonna have like right now
and so it's tricky it's hard I think
it's hard to have novelty in monogamy
and it certainly easier just to find a
new person who's just like new and then
you can like be okay that obviously new
and that's nice and I love novelty learn
that way like I love other sex with new
people like I think it's exciting to
have sex with the person you never had
sex with before and it's a but it's also
exciting to have sex with a person
you've had sex before in a new way or in
a braver way and that just requires just
going deeper and deeper and deeper all
the time which is kind of vertiginous
you know like like I'm dizzy how can I
go deeper I've gone as deep as I can go
I don't know that there's any deeper to
go but there always is and so I don't
know I've know like I don't
I'm agnostic about monogamy polygamy
like I I see both I see the value of
both spiritual paths
but I think novelty is needed in either
one
yeah it makes me think of what you said
about um normally when we watch the
garbage can we have no awareness of
other possibilities apart from the
regular completion of the garbage can
tasks and as as sad as it might sound I
think often in in long-term
relationships whether they're monogamous
or non-monogamous we sort of approach
sex in the same way a lot of times we
have kind of a routine and that routine
doesn't necessarily vary a lot anymore
because we find a way that is like the
least vulnerable and that becomes the
path of least resistance but it's also
the least sexy um one thing that your
filmmaking is really good at is like
presenting vulnerability even when it's
not what would be in anybody's comfort
zone how do you feel like that has
improved your sex life amassing
vulnerability and and and sex sexual
lists are related you know like I think
I think not vulnerable sex is not as
exciting or sexual or sexy or sensual as
vulnerable sex and and I think and
that's not just true of sex is true of
any interaction I'm it's true of just a
conversation it's true of a conversation
with a stranger on the street you know
like there's something a vulnerability
that is so sexy I don't know it's like
and they're like and and it makes you
fall in love with the person I mean I
think I think we fall in love with
vulnerable nests you know like it's
people's vulnerability that we love in
them it's not their you know it's not
their accomplishments or their strengths
really it's their and even in a movie
you know like the scenes that you love
and are the scenes where something was
broken or something was opened that you
know your own heart could pour into so I
think vulnerability is
yeah I mean there's of course there's
you know people who are into like you
know masochism and bondage and stuff but
and I'm not really a sniper really been
a world that I've explored much but I
imagine that even in that world there's
like all this vulnerability around the
trappings of invulnerability you know so
I don't know it just seems like it's
kind of the key ingredient in connection
and in an in ear us really um it we're
getting kind of close that half hour
mark so I'm gonna open it up to
questions
I'll let Peter start if he'd like to a
mute himself thanks maybe so my original
question was what is your current theory
on monogamy but you kind of touched on
that so I'm gonna modify the question so
you you came in my previous podcast
twice and the second time was with
talking with Chester Brown and you guys
had sort of jesse brown four people
don't know he's a graphic novelist did a
bunch of amazing graphic novels one of
them called paying for it and then kinda
and Chester had sort like a debate non
debate about you know you kind of
approach this similar topic from
different positions so I guess my
question is since we last spoke
what has your theory on monogamy
relationship sexuality has it has it
changed at all it's always changing
based on whatever is happening you know
in my life you know I think maybe we'll
be okay with this but like Mia maybe had
a talk like a few like a few days ago
and we talked about sexual attraction
stuff with each other
and and and I said you know I'm seeing
this other person in Berlin and and and
maybe it was like you know I understand
you know this is a thing you know when
people are in a poly relationship you
know that people deal with and and I was
like okay I was worried I was worried
about that relationship like I don't
want to lose that relationship like I'm
really invested in it and I think
spiritually you know I think
so hard like you wanna you want to
protect the thing you value but you
don't want to you don't want to protect
at the expense of reality's unfolding
and so I was kind of in this place of
like um I should probably tell Valerie
about my conversation with maybe but I
was scared too because I didn't want to
alienate her or scare her away because I
was like just really wanted this
relationship to work out and because
it's long distance and it's in another
country there's no travel it's like I
have to keep it going for a while if I'm
gonna like get it to a place where like
they can be consummation of desire and
so I kind of like didn't talk about it
right away because I was kind of scared
I was scared to fuck with that and then
at a certain point I think I got I think
I got stoned and when I'm stoned I'm
fearless and I'm honest so in my stone
place I just talked about it and she has
this really great reaction and it was
like I don't know how I would feel like
I might feel like if something happened
with you and someone else
you know maybe or anyone uh you know I
don't know how I would feel about it I
might be really a lien ated and not want
to ever talk to you again or I might be
kind of turned on and be like this is
even more exciting like I just said I
don't know um and if I she was about to
go meet a friend I said if I went to saw
this friend and I said oh we had a great
time and we ended up having sex it was
great like how would you feel and I was
like oh wow I would I would part of me
would feel like a little insecure and
worried and probably be kind of excited
and feel like well this is kind of
exciting this person would seem to me
like more I don't call it like like I
think the other other and sacred and
powerful then they do when I'm trying to
protect them or have the notion of what
they need are trying to manage them or
you know like
and she suddenly went from being
somebody who I somehow is projecting
like a certain amount of neediness onto
or needing me to be a certain way to
somebody who was just like way cooler
and way sexier and it was kind of a
great shift and just showed me like how
I was starting to already fall into a
rut with this person that I've only been
talking to for a couple of weeks and
have never even met so I don't know what
the answer is I just know that being
honest
we'll take you to where you need to go I
think and and keeps it fresh keeps it
alive keeps it keeps it from falling
into you know stale projections yeah
that's what I was thinking it it creates
aliveness yeah yeah cool thank you I
have a follow-up question around that um
something that I really admire is that
she was able to express to you that she
didn't know how she would feel I think
that that is like such an exciting form
of honesty and I'd love to hear like how
it landed with you to have someone
expressed that that they didn't know how
they would feel about something yeah I
mean it was it was exciting and alive it
was like life like you don't know what's
gonna happen tomorrow you know you know
we could all die and that's kind of
great you know yeah I just it's just
like it brought me closer to her for
real like a brought me closer to the
real her as opposed to the fantasy her I
could just cut the fantasy out of the
equation and you know sexuality is a
weird mix of fantasy and and reality you
know it's kind of a dialectic between
those two things I think and it's kind
of what's great about it like if it's
all fantasy like it's it gets it gets
old and dead and and you know my
argument with Chester I think was kind
of about you know I think it came down
to fantasy you know like is there
something wrong with fantasy and of
course there isn't anything wrong with
fantasy but there it becomes a problem
if the fantasy overwhelms reality and
becomes and reality becomes a
second-class citizen to fantasy and I
think for me and I think even Chester
said this in our in our talk like the
problem with whenever pornography or the
problem with prostitute stuff is more of
that you're kind of in a fantasy
relationship and to the extent that it
could be a real relationship except that
you could be real with a prostitute or
you know or real with this person that
you know then then it's not then that
problem isn't there then it's alive and
it's and it's an
connection but to the extent that is not
that that is just a a mask and a and a
transaction and then you just do the
rope thing that you know you've been
programmed to think to get off on you
know to the extent that's then it's
empty and and afterwards I feel empty
and I think I was saying to Chester I
always feel bad afterwards
and I think it's because that elements
of fantasy and it would accept that it
doesn't feel bad after this is when that
element is not there as much when the
feeling there was actually a connection
and you know with a prostitute you never
know if that was a real connection or
not you know like she could just be
really good at her job but but sometimes
you feel that you feel like I think
there was a real connection and you're
touched your heart is open and you're
like wow even though there was money
exchanged there there was still
something enlivening about that and
there was love or there was respect or
there was sacred sacred exchange it's
like you know sacred sex or you know the
you know ancient Greek you know sacred
prostitute energy but often you know the
woman isn't into it
she's not trying to be connecting she's
not trying to be open she's just trying
to get paid and yeah it's understandable
it's you know she's doing her job but
that's the way that's when it feels icky
I guess to me for my from my angle yeah
I agree it's I think a lot to do is what
you said before about how there's like a
very delicate balance between being
connected to the other person but also
connected to yourself and sort of having
your focus be in both of those places so
that you're sort of experiencing a unity
between the two of you that doesn't like
collapse the identity of either one
completely
I think fool Jeff has an interesting
question that can like tag on to this
would you like to unmute yourself hi I
feel actually okay leading up to taking
this question just because we're talking
about honesty that kind of nervous
asking this question but it seems like
so
with the practice of like radical
honesty it seems like you have this
moment where you are honest and then the
next time it seems like you almost
express the same thing thinking it's
honesty again but it's already become
not true and I was wondering like that's
one of the problems I've run into you as
wondering maybe what kind of problems
you've maybe run into with the practice
of radical honesty as well is that for
me yeah yeah thanks for that question
it's a good one I think you're right I
think you know you're honest and then
somehow the honesty gets ratified right
away you know and so it's like and you
have to kind of it's easy to think oh I
was honest and that's and that's the
truth and then it's like already not
true again or you know like in the next
second and I think I don't know it's
hard you just have to like keep calling
yourself out and tuning into like what
am i enough what am I feeling now you
know now what am I feeling and you know
and because I I said something I'm
actually feeling differently like
everything you say changes you're you
know the emotional temperature that you
have you know it's like you're always in
movement and so I could say I feel this
and then like as soon as I said it like
it feels something different and so how
do you keep that going it could be
exhausting I guess but yeah I think yeah
I think you need to do that I'm somebody
you know I'm willing to channeled
material and somebody once asked this
channel entity about tithing I was like
is it important to tithe and the
channeled entity said it's not important
to tithe what's important is to give in
the direction of your gratitude
and when you feel gratitude for someone
towards someone you should give right
then as you're feeling it and that's
what you should be doing not like having
ideas about you know I should give 10%
of my income to this charity you know
like just give as you feel it's
and I I try to do that and I've noticed
sometimes like I've I want to give and I
just don't get around to it and then
later I don't want it to anymore like
I've just passed the moment past my
moment of gratitude past and then
sometimes I still give anyway because I
wanted to give earlier and I know I
should give or wanted to give but now it
feels wrong and I feel resentful that
I'm giving because I don't feel it so um
I don't know except I just think you
should act right now when you feel
something because it's like that is the
time to act and it reminds me that Blake
thing about you know better to murder a
child in their bed than to not act on a
desire you know like it's just like
because something so sacred about a
desire and certainly a desire for
expression of love or gratitude
especially like wow you know that's so
precious it's like gold that kiddo do it
do it now you know tell them you love
them tell them give the show them your
love now you know because later you're
not you're not gonna feel it you're
gonna feel some other thing
I don't that answered your question but
I tried yeah this does really nice to
reflect on um I had another follower or
I had another question too just because
we had watched I am a sex addict
recently and you had actually said in it
like I'm worried 20 years from now I'm
gonna be in the same place I am now and
I know from watching the show of the
show you are getting divorced so I'm
just wondering if you I think it's a
story principle to get maybe what you're
afraid of to realize it has the power of
you and I wonder if you have any
reflection on that Wow that's a good
question I even think of that but yeah
it's been about 20 years and and I'm
kind of have recently been in that same
situation where I kind of like you know
for 20 years I was like not acting out
sexually with prostitutes and then like
after talking to Chester I was kind of
like oh he's kind of got a really good
point maybe this is okay to do and then
I remembered as soon as I did it like oh
I remember why I was trying not to do
this I just had forgotten you know it's
easy to forget because the ego is just
like this is gonna make you feel so much
better and then it doesn't but yeah I I
and I you know also when you're older
there's just something more honest I
mean all of us are gonna get there some
of us getting there before others but
there's something really hard about
sexuality and aging you know just like
you just feel like you're your trap you
know you decide oh you're attractiveness
to others diminishes with time and so
the things that you could do before to
be like I'm gonna affirm bisexual this
they just get harder and so yeah 20
years later it's like you don't want to
be that guy and I don't know I think I
think I'm not that guy only because I
have like a spiritual practice I have
some kind of inner healing that has
happened in those 20 years that makes it
feel different like the self-hatred the
shame the pathos has lifted to a large
extent so I have a certain equanimity
that I concern of whether the 20 years
after
before and after picture better you know
and that's nice and that's the result of
a lot of I think hard work you know like
spiritual practice call me I wonder if
you could touch a little bit on how
psychedelics have played a role in that
spiritual opening and discovery I mean
for me they've been key or essential I
mean I think I wouldn't be Who I am
without psychedelics I mean I think I
know who I would be but wouldn't be this
guy I would be a much angrier person I'd
be a much more rigid person yeah for me
psychedelics was my with my spiritual
path it was my pathway to to God to
nature to to art it's been everything
for me and I don't know I mean I think
it opened up you know the doors of
perception and I saw so many things I
saw my inner I saw my you know when I
was young I wanted to be an artist just
because it seemed like a cool thing to
be I mean I don't know why I wanted that
but you know I think everyone who wants
to be an artist at a certain point
they're not an artist yet so they're
like a wannabe artist and at a certain
point hopefully you two point you're
like oh alright maybe I am an artist now
but until then you're just kind of a
fraud you know you're you're pretending
to be an artist so you're positing the
you're an artist but are you really or
are you just like and is an artist like
something different than other people
and are you born into it or you know and
I remember when I started actually when
I when I discovered marijuana which was
in college you know get stoned and I
would see these incredible things that
were more beautiful anything I've ever
seen in my life and I was like who the
where what is this and it was like it's
it's my mind I was seeing my mind and my
mind was so much more beautiful than
anything I'd ever seen including my own
mind like I'd never seen my mind it's
kind of like I don't know I guess it's
like discovering your sexuality like
you're like whoa there's a I have a
penis and it can orgasm yeah whatever
like it was like I didn't know that was
there I didn't know that my mind
was doing that it was doing that at a
level that I wasn't aware of but then I
was like whoa I remember this is there's
this a talking head song I really like
memories can't wait and and David Byrne
says there's a party in my mind and I
hope it never stops there's a party in
there all the time gonna party till we
drop and I remember thinking like this
guy has a party in his mind like this
guy has a party I don't have a party
there's no party in my mind my mind is
just kind of like mmm you know humdrum
but he has a party and I wouldn't be
great to be him I just wanted to be him
because he had a party and I had no
party and I just thought he was you know
better than me or you know and then when
I got stoned I was like oh I have a
party to it and it's a great party like
it's it's as great a party as any party
can be and so I just I just discovered
my own inner artist and and that was
great and that really gave me so much
confidence and joy and and connection to
who I am and and to and to God into my
connection to God into my uniqueness and
in my sameness and just the whole
universal specificity that is each of us
so that was great and then also just
encountering God and being like whoa God
exists like God this God just you know
I've had experiences where it's just
like oh my fucking god it's true and the
magnificence of God and the power of God
and the tornado like you know explosion
that is God all of that you know
psychedelics and the next last thing is
just love like it's so clear that God is
just overwhelming love and I think I
think my life has sort of gone from
pursuing this ego dream of like
specialness and like you know I think as
soon as I wanted to make films which was
I was like 18 now it's just like I want
to be the greatest filmmaker ever and
it's only thought that because I was 18
and stupid but also because for me if I
wasn't the greatest filmmaker ever I
wasn't anything I was worthless like I
had very low self-esteem and I'd to
compensate for my low self-esteem by
some kind of grandiosity and so yeah I
spent most of my life trying to attain
this grandiosity to not feel bad about
my
but along the way through psychedelics
really I discovered that you know love
is the thing not specialness like
specialness is nothing I mean no one is
special where else we're all equally
special and there is no greatest
filmmaker you know it's absurd concept
obviously but um love is the important
thing I mean like it's the only thing
and and all the the vainglory dreams you
know of glory of vainglory I've have
receded you know I still have them you
know like I still would love to have
people think I'm a great filmmaker
somebody wrote the other day and Twitter
thing says something like Kavya Haiti is
the greatest filmmaker for the next
several generations and I was like yay
but you know it's not important anymore
it's just like oh that's fun someone
thinks that but it's not like I need
that to feel okay and so now I can just
pursue what's important and I think I
just just love in every moment and just
the enjoyment of the moment and I think
also like I wanted to be an artist and I
wanted the acclaim of being an artist
and I always wanted to finish like I
wanted to art to be done so I could get
rid of it so I could just get to the
acclaim but I think what I really wanted
was just to live in the sphere of art
just to feel feel art in my daily moment
like to be art to be art through my
fingertips like that's that's what I
really wanted but I thought it had to be
some kind of product that I then
persuaded the people was was worthy of
something and it's like no it's just
like how can I be artistic in this
moment with with you guys like how can I
be honest and real and and loving and
and receive your love you know so that's
all psychedelics very trippy um
Chelsea has a really brilliant question
I'd love if you could unmute yourself
and ask hai kabhi um my question is how
do you find love in a friendship where
there is de presentment yeah I'm having
that at the moment
yeah yeah story of my life too I mean I
think resentment is the opposite of love
and I think resentment kills
relationships it's like it's a
relationship killer right and so I used
to think the only way to make a
relationship work is if you could
constantly clear the resentment you know
everything that comes up he was clear it
and you clear right away you know it's
like don't go to bed until you've
cleared the resentment and when I was
married for 20 years you know my wife
did not share that view
she had this other view that was like
you know you can just live with it it's
gonna be okay we'll deal with it later
and I was like no no we're gonna break
up we're gonna break up if we don't
clear it now you know and and you know
took a while but we broke up and we
broke up because of resentments because
the resentments just piled up to the
point where nobody could could you you
the hatred was so thick you know and
there was nothing left there was no love
left and all that resentment so I think
resentment is like you know public enemy
number one and I think whatever you can
do to get rid of it I don't know I mean
I think you have to be honest about the
resentments first of all and if the
person can't handle that I think that's
the end of the friendship early Ivy a
friendship I think I think the division
of a friendship is somebody with whom
you can say what you need to say and
they can hear it and a lot of people
that's not the case and I think those
are not friends you know those are
acquaintances I guess or you know maybe
strategic allies in your quest for
whatever you're going for but a friend
is somebody you can say hey I'm really
mad at you you really hurt my feelings
and I'm really having a hard time with
this thing that just happened and I'm
feeling alienated or something and if
the person can say oh you are I'm sorry
why what can I do gonna you know or I'm
kind of mad at you too about something
and I think that's why I did that and
here's what I'm mad about and you can
you can work it out and get to a place
where you understand that person and why
they did it and you can drop the
resentment if you can't do that you
can't be friends I think so a lot of
people can't be friends with it's sad
but I think that's the truth and I think
the hard thing is how do you express a
resentment in a way that isn't resentful
right yeah
and people have written books on this
and they do it better than I do it
but you know what they all say you know
you have to talk about how how you feel
and not put it on them at all like it's
like I'm having a problem
you know I need help can you help me I
need your help I'm having this
resentment or anger that I don't want to
have and I'm not you didn't it's not
your fault it's not you know I just I
need help and so they say that you can
do that and really own it then they can
to that extent they can hear it better
not that they can some people can't hear
anything any kind of criticism or any
kind of anything they just can't because
their self-esteem is so low that if
that's there they just they just
collapse oh they hate themselves too
much you know and again I don't think
you can be friends with those people
um but yeah that's such a hard one
I'm sorry here I'm sorry you're feeling
it that's okay thanks everyone I think
yeah yeah I mean I'm I have a whole list
of people that resentment stores and I'm
just trying to like reduce the list and
I feel like when I can get the list to
zero I'm good like I can I can die now
I've accomplished my task in life yeah
good luck thank you thank you on John
has question as well I'd love if you
could unmute yourself on John uh not
much of a question cafe it's just like a
I guess a random thought have you in
your own life ever felt value or learned
from conservative cultures or practices
for example like arranged marriages I'm
not showing gestures of love in public
etc etc and do you think there's
anything to be learned I mean it's
probably set to be learned from anything
you know my knee-jerk reaction is always
you know arranged marriage is bad you
know not sure he love gestures public
bad you know like I have a knee jerk you
know thing towards you know whatever a
kind of on an uninhibited expression of
whatever but I do
I mean what's interesting about arranged
marriages is you know the statistics
that they're just as successful as under
managed marriages and you know what does
that mean I mean it seems like it means
that
basically you really could be with just
about anybody I mean everyone is like
lovable and everyone is equally
fucked-up and equally great at sub level
and it's really just a choice of who you
decide you're gonna like work with you
know in your in your practice and I
really believe that everything happens
for a reason I think the people in our
lives come to us because they're they're
appropriate people so an arranged
marriage isn't arranged I mean you say
it's arranged by the parents but it's
really arranged by God you know like God
got that going not the parents so in
that sense it's like sure if God says
you marry this person it's just like you
know you meeting someone on tinder you
know and then responding to your like
you know it's like it's also God you
know so I think the universe is like a
big matchmaker and whenever we're like
hit a new level that we were ready for a
new something to learn then they send
that person to us and loves it's
negative love it's like you need to look
at this hard lesson and we're gonna send
somebody's gonna like fuck with you now
but yeah there's something I think
there's something good about that model
just because it shows the limits of the
you know freedom model that you know
Western society sort of believes in and
that has you know has a place in the
dialectic of history but it's not this
area the be-all and end-all either you
know it's like just a phase in the
dialectic of of moving towards God I
don't know is that answer your question
any any other thing you want to ask or
add to that that's pretty interesting
hearing you talk about Thanks I have a
follow-up question for your on that um
one of the things that comes to mind
when you talk about really different
circumstances being difficult to
understand but having similar results is
your philosophy that there's a way in
which we can take radical responsibility
for our own experiences at least on this
like spiritual level I'd love to hear
you talk a little bit about that about
like responsibility for our experience
like our physical external experience
especially like around your trouble or
dislike for boundaries and how like it's
because on some level boundaries are not
acknowledging that we are radically
responsible for our own emotions and
experiences in the world yeah I mean I
mean I think I'm like a lot of people I
think I'm somebody who doesn't take
responsibility for my experience
generally you know like I'm usually
resentful about my experience and I'm
blaming other people you know whether
it's my ex-wife or the my boss or you
know the person who just was mean to me
on the street you know it's like I'm mad
at them and and I think you know when
I'm in a spiritual mindset and I'm
having faith that things are for a
reason then I'm able to just kind of be
like oh okay what how how did I create
that or how is that something that is a
you know and this is such a such a
radical idea I mean it's such a radical
idea that it's almost inconceivable and
it's it's really hard to to accept it
really I think it's been really hard for
me certainly but I you know I sort of
believe it and I sort of try to live by
it but you know I fail and I flail you
know constantly but um but yeah you know
like I think I've really been lonely for
the past you know three years since my
breakup and I've had a hard time finding
a lover a companion uh whatever and and
you know you ask yourself like is
something wrong with me
is it me am I is something in me that is
not creating whatever abundance or
whatever love reciprocity energy that
would manifest as a lover that you know
that loves you and that once what you
want and then wants to have sex with you
and and I've been you know doing
spiritual practice and really trying to
like manifest you know I think I think
desire is sacred and I think it's okay
to
it's not only locators I think you have
to desire what you want and and in
desiring it without without guilt and
without obfuscation and without any kind
of undercurrent you do manifest it in
your life and I think for me like I've
been having these kind of like whatever
sexual encounters over the past year
let's say that has become increasingly
close to hitting the mark
and none of they've hit the mark but
each one gets a little closer to the
mark and I feel like those uh those n
archers who like blindfold themselves
and they spin around and then they try
to hit the bull's eye without seeing and
like I feel like I'm getting better at
it and like every time I have a new
relationship it's a little closer to
like a satisfying one than the one
before and I'm still not there yet
because I've manifested somebody and in
Berlin that I can't actually be with
uh-huh but but it's a really good one
and so it's like you know that's the
closest I've been and the one before
that was you know I had some really
better than the one before it misses to
it so I feel like I move I'm getting you
know it's some kind of mantra every day
I'm getting better and better what is
that thing you know like in every way
like I feel that way about sex and love
like I'm a manifesting more love in my
life and more attraction in my life and
I think that's me in my inner being
affirming it wanting it and also doing
the things that are undoing the things
that are preventing it you know but
inside so does that answer your question
I'm not sure yeah it does I absolutely
like track what you're saying we're
about two minutes to the hour and so my
last question that I want to ask you is
what what's your honest feeling about
having been here for this first episode
of the raw sexuality series how is this
felt for you really enlivening I mean
I'm feeling good I'm uh I'm sweating a
little bit because it's hot but I really
I feel good I think I'm gonna walk away
with with a bounce in my step
I'm hearing you say that I know I'm
gonna walk away with a bounce in my step
- oh that makes me so happy
um Peter I want to ask is there anything
that you want to plug before we end the
session yeah I just want to say
excellent job maybe for launching this
series it was a wonderful emceeing and
kind of a my friend for coming back to
the store that was I felt alive just
witnessing that and being a part of it
so thank you both
yeah so uh upcoming events of the store
I guess I'll just pluck one or two we
were doing things every Tuesday
Wednesday Thursday called stoic hustle
from 10:00 a.m. to 3:00 p.m. Eastern
time and it's like as interesting
modality where we kind of work together
in silence and we all see each other in
the zoo and we we have a structure like
30 minute time period five minute break
and it's been really fun as a way to
build community Oz while we hustle
together on on getting shit done and
then tomorrow we have James cars from
the finite if innoGames he's giving talk
on playing the infinite game during the
meta-crisis that's 3 p.m. Eastern time
tomorrow and aa recipe on the website so
you wanna close up maybe you know take
you back in yeah awesome thank you guys
all for being here I'm really excited to
bring more sessions on like sexuality
and authenticity thank you so much for
being in my first event and I hope that
you guys felt some raw vulnerable sexual
energy in the past hour see you guys
around
bye thank you you wanna debrief for a
minute Kavi was maybe oh sure
stop record